<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Revision: 1.5 $ -->
<classentry id="pango.pangofontfamily">
 <classmeta>
  <classtitle>PangoFontFamily</classtitle>
  <classparent>GObject</classparent>
  <shortdesc>
    Used to represent a family of related font faces.
  </shortdesc>
  <desc>
    <para>
      The <classname>PangoFontFamily</classname> object is used to represent a
      family of related font faces. The faces in a family share a common design,
      but differ in slant, weight, width and other aspects. An array of
      <classname>PangoFontFamily</classname> objects can be retrieved from a
      <classname>PangoContext</classname> object using the
      <function class="PangoContext">list_families</function> method or from a
      <classname>PangoFontMap</classname> object using
      the <function class="PangoFontMap">list_families</function> method.
    </para>
  </desc>
 </classmeta>

 <methods>

  <method id="pango.pangofontfamily.method.get_name">
   <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
     <funcdef>string <function>get_name</function></funcdef>
     <paramdef>void</paramdef>
    </funcprototype>
   </funcsynopsis>
   <shortdesc>
    Returns a string containing the name of the font family.
   </shortdesc>
   <desc>
    <para>
      This method returns a string containing the name of the font family. The
      name is unique among all fonts for the font backend and can be used in a
      <classname>PangoFontDescription</classname> to specify that a face from
      this family is desired.
    </para>
   </desc>
  </method>

  <method id="pango.pangofontfamily.method.is_monospace">
   <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
     <funcdef>bool <function>is_monospace</function></funcdef>
     <paramdef>void</paramdef>
    </funcprototype>
   </funcsynopsis>
   <shortdesc>
    Returns <literal>True</literal> if the font is monospace.
   </shortdesc>
   <desc>
    This method returns <literal>True</literal> if the font family describes a
    monospace font. A monospace font is a font designed for text display where
    the the characters form a regular grid. For Western languages this would
    mean that the advance width of all characters are the same, but this
    categorization also includes Asian fonts which include double-width
    characters: characters that occupy two grid cells.
   </desc>
  </method>

  <method id="pango.pangofontfamily.method.list_faces">
   <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
     <funcdef>void <function>list_faces</function></funcdef>
     <paramdef>void</paramdef>
    </funcprototype>
   </funcsynopsis>
   <shortdesc>
    Returns an array of <classname>PangoFontFace</classname> objects.
   </shortdesc>
   <desc>
    <para>
      This method returns an array of the different
      <classname>PangoFontFace</classname> objects that make up the font family.
      The faces in a family share a common design, but differ in slant, weight,
      width and other aspects.
    </para>
   </desc>
  </method>

 </methods>

</classentry>

