<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<chapter id="tutorials.gtkpangoco">
 <title>Gtk, Pango &amp; Co</title>
 
 <sect1>
  <simpara>
   When programming PHP-Gtk applications and surfing through the manual,
   you will find some rather cryptic acronyms. Here is the explanation for
   the most important ones.
  </simpara>
  
  <sect2>
   <title>PHP</title>
   <simpara>
    PHP is a widely-used general-purpose scripting language that 
    is especially suited for Web development and can be embedded into HTML.
   </simpara>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2>
   <title>GTK</title>
   <simpara>
    GTK+ is a library for creating graphical user interfaces. 
    It works on many UNIX-like platforms, Windows, and on framebuffer devices.
   </simpara>
   <simpara>
    The GTK+ library itself contains widgets, that is, 
    GUI components such as <classname>GtkButton</classname> or 
    <classname>GtkTextView</classname>.
   </simpara>
   <simpara>
    It depends on the other libraries like GDK, Pango, Atk and GLib.
   </simpara>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2>
   <title>GDK</title>
   <simpara>
    GDK is the abstraction layer that allows GTK+ to support multiple 
    windowing systems. GDK provides drawing and window system 
    facilities on X11, Windows, and the Linux framebuffer device.
   </simpara>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2>
   <title>Pango</title>
   <simpara>
    Pango is a library for internationalized text handling. 
    It centers around the <classname>PangoLayout</classname> object, representing a 
    paragraph of text. Pango provides the engine for 
    <classname>GtkTextView</classname>, <classname>GtkLabel</classname>, 
    <classname>GtkEntry</classname>, and other widgets that display text.
   </simpara>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2>
   <title>Atk</title>
   <simpara>
    ATK is the Accessibility Toolkit. It provides a set of generic 
    interfaces allowing accessibility technologies to interact with a 
    graphical user interface.
   </simpara>
   <simpara>
    For example, a screen reader uses ATK to discover the text 
    in an interface and read it to blind users. 
    GTK+ widgets have built-in support for accessibility using the ATK framework.
   </simpara>
  </sect2>
  
 </sect1>
</chapter> 
 
