<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!-- $Revision: 1.12 $ -->
<chapter id="tutorials.installation">
 <title>Installing PHP-GTK 2</title>

 <sect1 id="tutorials.installation.introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
   PHP-GTK 2 is an extension to PHP and can be used only with versions 5.1
   upwards. Although the most common way of installing PHP-GTK 2 is compiling,
   this process can prove to be quite tedious on Windows systems; in which
   case most people will be using the official PHP-GTK 2 Alpha binary release
   or the Gnope installer.
  </para>
  <para>
   We'll be covering the installation process for the three most popular
   operating systems: Windows, Linux and Mac OS X. The instructions for Linux
   are applicable to most distributions in addition to other POSIX compliant
   systems.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="tutorials.installation.windows">
  <title>Installation on Windows</title>

  <sect2 id="tutorials.installation.windows.gnope">
   <title>Using Gnope</title>
   <para>
    Gnope has proven to be the most easiest way of installing and maintaining
    PHP-GTK 2 on Windows. Gnope is a fully featured PHP-GTK 2 installer,
    complete with PHP 5.1, GTK 2.6 and PEAR.
    A few simple mouse clicks and you're done!
   </para>
   <para>
    Just download the installer from <ulink url="&url.gnope;">gnope.org</ulink>
    and follow the on-screen instructions. Gnope also has a PEARified channel
    of its own, where you can download PHP-GTK 2 applications, in addition to
    official PEAR packages, e.g. from the
    <ulink url="&url.pear.gtk2;">Gtk2 category</ulink>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="tutorials.installation.windows.manual">
   <title>Manual Installation</title>
   <para>
    Download the Alpha binary release of PHP-GTK 2 for Windows from the
    PHP-GTK 2 <ulink url="&url.phpgtk.download;">download</ulink> page. Unzip
    the file into a directory of your choice. A directory named
    <literal>php-gtk</literal> will be created containing everything included
    in the release.
   </para>
   <para>
    You will need a copy of <filename>php.exe</filename> (CLI Version) and
    <filename>php5ts.dll</filename>, both of which are available in the binary
    release of PHP 5 for windows, and put them in the
    <filename>php-gtk</filename> directory. If you wish to use any other
    extensions with this copy of <filename>php.exe</filename>, make sure you
    put their binaries here too.
   </para>
   <para>
    <!-- FIXME: Do we need to do this? I doubt that this is necessary
       -cweiske -->
    After this, you must set your <literal>PATH</literal> variable to include
    the <filename>gtk+2.6.9</filename> directory present in the release.
    You can also let the <literal>gtkpath.bat</literal> batch file set the
    appropriate <literal>PATH</literal> for the current command line
    session by executing it.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="tutorials.installation.windows.cvs">
   <title>Compiling from CVS</title>
   <para>
    This is the least recommended method of installing PHP-GTK 2 on Windows.
    If you still want to go ahead with this, please read
    <filename>win32/README.win32.txt</filename> in the CVS checkout.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="tutorials.installation.linux">
  <title>Installation on Linux</title>

  <para>
   The best way to install PHP-GTK 2 on Linux is to compile it. No binary or
   source packages are available as yet for any distribution, so you can't use
   your favorite package manager to install PHP-GTK 2! These instructions
   should be valid for most distributions of Linux, as well as other POSIX
   compliant systems.
  </para>

  <note>The methods listed here reportedly don't work on FreeBSD</note>

  <para>
   There are two ways to go about installing PHP-GTK 2 on your Linux system.
   You can either choose to use your existing PHP installation, or decide to
   install a separate one and dedicate it to PHP-GTK 2. The latter is a simpler
   method and is recommended for users with little or no Linux experience.
   In any case, you need Gtk+ version 2.6 upwards installed.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="tutorials.installation.linux.newphp">
   <title>Installing PHP-GTK 2 along with a new PHP installation</title>

   <para>
    Just follow these steps, and you should be okay! First thing you need 
    is a fresh checkout of PHP. You can choose either the
    <literal>5_1</literal> or <literal>5_2</literal> branches,
    both work fine:

    <programlisting role="bash"><![CDATA[
$ cvs -d :pserver:cvsread@cvs.php.net:/repository login
$ cvs -d :pserver:cvsread@cvs.php.net:/repository co -r PHP_5_2 php-src]]></programlisting>

     Now, you need to compile and install it:

     <programlisting role="bash"><![CDATA[
$ cd php-src
$ ./buildconf
$ ./configure --prefix=/opt/php5_2 --disable-cgi
$ make
$ su
$ make install
$ echo extension=php_gtk2.so >> /opt/php5_2/lib/php.ini
$ /opt/php5_2/bin/php-config --extension-dir | xargs echo 'extension_dir=' >> /opt/php5_2/lib/php.ini]]></programlisting>
   </para>

   <note>
    <para>
     If the current CVS of PHP does not compile, try an
     official release from the
     <ulink url="&url.php.download;">php downloads page</ulink>,
     or a <ulink url="&url.php.snapshots;">snapshot</ulink>.
    </para>
   </note>

   <para>
    Now, let's checkout and install PHP-GTK 2:
    <programlisting role="bash"><![CDATA[
$ cd ..
$ cvs -d :pserver:cvsread@cvs.php.net:/repository co php-gtk
$ cd php-gtk
$ ./buildconf --with-phpize=/opt/php5_2/bin/phpize
$ ./configure --with-php-config=/opt/php5_2/bin/php-config
$ make
$ make install]]></programlisting>
   </para>

   <para>
    You might want to create a link to the new php executable:

    <programlisting role="bash"><![CDATA[
$ ln -s /opt/php5_2/bin/php /usr/bin/php-gtk]]></programlisting>

    That's it, you're done!
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="tutorials.installation.linux.existingphp">
   <title>Using an existing PHP installation</title>

   <para>
    If you decide to 'add-on' PHP-GTK 2 to your existing PHP installation,
    ensure that your version of PHP is at least 5.1 with CLI enabled.
    PHP-GTK 2 will NOT work with any other versions of PHP.
    You can check your PHP version by typing <command>php -v</command>
    on the command line. Don't forget to check if the word
    <literal>cli</literal> appears in the output!
   </para>

   <para>
    Now, checkout the latest CVS source of PHP-GTK 2, or download the Alpha
    source tarball, as per instructions on the PHP-GTK 2
    <ulink url="&url.phpgtk.download;">download</ulink> page.
    <literal>cd</literal> into the checked out / extracted directory, and
    execute the following:
    <programlisting role="bash"><![CDATA[
$ ./buildconf
$ ./configure
$ make
$ make install]]></programlisting>
   </para>

   <para>
    This should just work for most people. However, if there are multiple
    installations of PHP in your machine or you have installed PHP in some
    exotic location, you might face trouble. Most of these cases can be solved
    by specifying the exact locations of the <literal>phpize</literal> and
    <literal>php-config</literal> files:
    <programlisting role="bash"><![CDATA[
$ ./buildconf --with-phpize=/path/to/phpize
$ ./configure --with-php-config=/path/to/php-config]]></programlisting>
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="tutorials.installation.linux.testing">
   <title>Testing your installation</title>

   <para>
    Before you can use PHP-GTK 2, you need to enable the extension in
    your <filename>php.ini</filename>. Just add a
    <programlisting role="ini"><![CDATA[
extension=php_gtk2.so]]></programlisting>
     below all the other <literal>extension=</literal> settings.
   </para>

   <para>
    You can test whether your installation was successful by executing:

    <programlisting role="bash"><![CDATA[
$ php -m | grep php-gtk]]></programlisting>

    You should get a single line that reads <literal>php-gtk</literal>.
   </para>

   <para>
    Next, you can try out the demo applications in the
    <filename>demos</filename> directory of the php-gtk sources,
    e.g. <filename>demos/phpgtk2-demo.php</filename>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="tutorials.installation.macosx">
  <title>Installation on Mac OS X</title>

  <para>
   You need to make sure you have the Apple Developer Tools, BSD Subsystem,
   and an installation of X before you try installing PHP-GTK 2. Although
   the BSD subsystem is installed by default on Mac OS X, you need select
   the Developer Tools and X Server manually. Although you can use any X
   server, the easiest would be to use the one Apple provides by default on
   it's Mac OS X installer.
  </para>

  <para>
   Get <ulink url="&url.macports;">MacPorts</ulink> (previously knows as
   DarwinPorts) or <ulink url="&url.fink;">Fink</ulink> and install it. You
   can use either to install a version of X (if you decided not to use
   Apple's default distribution), and Gtk+ itself. Both Fink and MacPorts
   provide versions 2.6 and above of Gtk+. Also make sure you have a version
   of PHP that is atleast 5.2, MacPorts provides a package. Type
   <literal>php -v</literal> on your Terminal to find out your version.
   If you want to manually compile PHP you can do so:

   <programlisting role="bash"><![CDATA[
$ cvs -d :pserver:cvsread@cvs.php.net:/repository co -r PHP_5_2 php-src
$ cd php-src
$ ./buildconf
$ ./configure --disable-cgi
$ make
$ sudo make install]]></programlisting>
   Although you may install it anywhere, <filename>/usr/local/</filename> is
   usually considered a good place. MacPorts installs PHP into
   <filename>/opt/local/</filename>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Now get the latest checkout of PHP-GTK and compile it:

   <programlisting role="bash"><![CDATA[
$ cd..
$ cvs -d :pserver:cvsread@cvs.php.net:/repository co php-gtk
$ cd php-gtk
$ ./buildconf --with-phpize=/usr/local/bin/phpize
$ ./configure --with-php-config=/usr/local/bin/php-config \
            --disable-libglade
$ make
$ sudo make install]]></programlisting>
   Remember to replace <filename>/usr/local/</filename> with the actual directory
   in which you installed PHP. For example, if you installed PHP 5.2 using
   MacPorts, you would enter <filename>/opt/local/</filename> instead.
  </para>

  <para>
   Finally, copy over the <filename>php.ini-recommended</filename> file
   to <filename>/usr/local/lib/php.ini</filename> and change the value of
   <literal>extension_dir</literal> to the directory where
   <literal>php_gtk2.so</literal> resides. This is usually something like:
   <literal>/usr/local/lib/php/extensions/no-debug-non-zts-some-date</literal>.
   You may want to create a new symbolic link in <filename>/usr/bin/</filename>
   that points to <filename>/usr/local/bin/php</filename>. Again, the directory
   may be <filename>/opt/local/</filename> instead of
   <filename>/usr/local/</filename> depending on where your installation of PHP
   resides.
  </para>

  <para>
   Now continue with
   <link linkend="tutorials.installation.linux.testing">Testing
   your installation</link>.
  </para>
 </sect1>


 <sect1 id="tutorials.installation.macosx-stepbystep">
  <title>Installation on Mac OS X - step by step</title>
  <para>Written by Jonathan Richter</para>

  <para>
   In an attempt to get PHP-GTK2 to work on Mac OS X 10.4, I found
   very little information and support on that subject.
   After a lot of failures and errors I got it to work.
  </para>
  <para>
   Below I'll write every step I took. I am not very comfortable with Terminal
   and half of the time I have no clue what I am doing.
   So you can use this information but totally on your own risk.
   I just worked for me. I hope it will help anybody else too.
  </para>

  <note>
   <para>
    please be adviced that doing all steps below takes several hours.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   Resources I found helpful:
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link linkend="tutorials.installation.macosx">The previous installation page</link>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://www.macports.org/">macports.org</ulink>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <sect2>
   <title>Step 1 - Get Xcode</title>
   <para>
    Get the newest Xcode (also called: Developer Tools) from Apple.
    You really need this. Go to
    <ulink url="https://connect.apple.com">connect.apple.com</ulink>.
    Sign in or sign up (for free). Go to Downloads.
   </para>
   <para>
    On the right in the Downloads Box, click Developer Tools and download the newest
    Xcode. In my case version 2.4.1, 923 MB big.
    After downloading, use the installer and follow the instructions.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Step 2 - Get Macports</title>
   <para>
    I started with using Fink, but halfway it failed by not having
    a package that was needed (GTK 2.6 or higher).
    I started all over using Macports.
   </para>
   <para>
    Go to
    <ulink url="http://trac.macosforge.org/projects/macports/wiki/InstallingMacPorts">macosforge/InstallingMacPorts</ulink>.
   </para>
   <para>
    You already did part of the first step by downloading Xcode.
    I followed all instructions on that page and it worked fine.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     The newest version didn't have a normal Apple installer. So I downloaded this:
     <ulink url="http://svn.macosforge.org/repository/macports/downloads/DarwinPorts-1.3.1/DarwinPorts-1.3.1-10.4.dmg">DarwinPorts-1.3.1-10.4.dmg</ulink>
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    Install Macports by double-clicking the installer in the disk image.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Step 3 - Get GTK2 (also called GTK+)</title>
   <para>
    In Terminal, type:
    <command>sudo port install gtk2</command>
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Step 4 - Get PHP5.x</title>
   <para>
    I already had a standard OS X PHP 4.4.4 installation and a
    PHP5 installation from <ulink url="http://www.entropy.ch">Entropy.ch</ulink>,
    but it didn't work out. I deleted my PHP5 installation from Entropy.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     If you want to run Apache 1 or 2 with PHP4 or 5, Entropy
     is absolutely the best place to get it.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    In Terminal, type:
    <command>cd /</command> and
    <command>sudo port install php5</command>
   </para>
   <para>
    Take a coffee, this takes a while... about 2 hours on my machine.
    (Macports installs everything in a folder called 
    <filename>/opt</filename>. I put the "cd /" to place that folder
    in the root.)
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Step 5 - Prepare for PHP-GTK</title>
   <para>
    On the other tutorial, you see a <literal>--disable-libglade</literal> as
    a parameter for installing PHP-GTK. I don't know why they wrote that.
    Be very sure that you really don't want Glade. Read about it here:
    <ulink url="http://glade.gnome.org">glade.gnome.org</ulink>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Check out the screenshots too. I installed without Glade but after
    a day I did it all over to get Glade working too.
    If you want to continue without Glade, skip the next step.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Step 6 - Get Glade</title>
   <para>
    For some reason, I got errors doing this. Then I tried again the same
    in Terminal, but now with X11 open in the background with no errors
    this time. So, open X11 and hide it (apple-h).
   </para>
   <para>
    In Terminal, type:
    <screen>
cd /opt
sudo port install libglade
sudo port install glade
    </screen>
     Take another coffee...
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Step 7 - Getting PHP-GTK2</title>
   <note>
    <para>
     Instead of using current CVS, you might want to use the latest
     official version from the
     <ulink url="http://gtk.php.net/download.php">PHP-GTK2 download page</ulink>.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    Leave X11 open to be on the safe side.
    <command>phpize</command> and <command>php-config</command> should be
    both in <filename>/opt/local/bin/</filename>.
    Check that before you run this. In Terminal, type:
    <screen>
sudo cvs -d :pserver:cvsread@cvs.php.net:/repository co php-gtk
cd php-gtk
sudo ./buildconf --with-phpize=/opt/local/bin/phpize
sudo ./configure --with-php-config=/opt/local/bin/php-config
sudo make
sudo make install
    </screen>
   </para>
   <para>
    After it is done, you will see in the output of Terminal a remark
    about extensions being installed with a path that probably looks
    like this:
    <filename>/opt/local/lib/php/extensions/no-debug-non-zts-20060613</filename>.
    Apple-c that path or write it down. You will need it later.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Step 8 - Make php.ini ready</title>
   <para>
    In Finder, choose Go &gt; Go To Folder... (or press shift-apple-g)
    and type <literal>/opt/local/etc</literal>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Find the file <filename>php.ini-recommended</filename> and copy it.
    Rename the copy to <filename>php.ini</filename> and open it with
    - preferably - BBedit.
   </para>
   <para>
    Find the line <literal>extension_dir = "./"</literal> and replace it with this:
    <literal>extension_dir = "/opt/local/lib/php/extensions/no-debug-non-zts-20060613"</literal>
    (That path, you copied from the Terminal output in the previous step)
   </para>
   <para>
    Find the block with all extensions and add this line after them:
    <literal>extension=php_gtk2.so</literal>
   </para>
   <para>
    Save the file.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Step 9 - Testing</title>
   <para>
    Start X11 and hide it (apple-h) if not already done.
   </para>
   <para>
    Start Terminal and type:
    <screen>
cd /opt/php-gtk/demos
php phpgtk2-demo.php
    </screen>
    The demo should open in a window in X11.
   </para>
   <para>
    To work with Glade, start it in Terminal like this (with X11 open):
    <command>/opt/local/bin/glade-2</command>
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Step 10 - Making it look better</title>
   <para>
    In my humble opinion: the interfaces in X11 look like crap
    when you are used to working in OS X.
    To get other themes, go to
    <ulink url="http://art.gnome.org/themes/gtk2">art.gnome.org</ulink>
    to check them out. In order to use one of those, we need to do one
    more step.
   </para>
   <para>
    In Terminal, type:
    <command>sudo port install gtk-theme-switch</command>
   </para>
   <para>
    After that is ready, download a theme from the link above.
    Installing it can be done in two ways:
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Move or copy the downloaded <filename>.tar.gz</filename>
       (without unpacking!) into <filename>/opt/local/share/themes/</filename>
      </para>
      <para>
       Start Glade by typing this in Terminal (with X11 open):
       <command>/opt/local/bin/switch2</command>
      </para>
      <para>
       Press the + sign and click the Install New Theme button.
       Point to <filename>/opt/local/share/themes/&lt;your-new-theme-name&gt;.tar.gz</filename>
      </para>
      <para>
       Click OK and now your new theme shows up in the list.
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       Unpack the <filename>&lt;your-new-theme-name&gt;.tar.gz</filename>
       and move or copy the new theme folder to
       <filename>/opt/local/share/themes/</filename>
      </para>
      <para>
       Start Glade by typing this in Terminal (with X11 open):
       <command>/opt/local/bin/switch2</command>
      </para>
      <para>
       The name of the new theme should be in the list.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <para>
    Again, I got it to work on my machines with above steps.
    My configs: iMac G5 2.0 GHz/1 GB RAM/OS X 10.4.8 and
    Mac mini G4 1.42 GHz/512 MB RAM/OS X 10.4.8.
    Please, fellow Mac users, post here any remarks, tips, tricks,
    etc. Let's get the PHP-GTK spirit to OS X too! Good hunting!
   </para>
  </sect2>

 </sect1>
</chapter>
