<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!-- $Revision: 1.4 $ -->
<book id="preface">
 <title>Preface</title>
  <simpara>
   Welcome to the user manual of PHP-GTK 2! This manual should help you get
   started with PHP-GTK 2 and also provide a comprehensive reference to most
   aspects of the language.
  </simpara>
  <simpara>
   This manual is split into two main parts. The first part is the 
   <link linkend="tutorials">Tutorials</link> section. This part will help you
   get started with PHP-GTK 2 programming and provide some insight into the
   various aspects of designing applications with PHP-GTK 2. The other part is
   the <link linkend="reference">Reference</link> section. This part of the
   manual provides details on all GTK objects and their associated methods and
   signals. This should be useful whenever you are in doubt of how a particular
   method or object is used.
  </simpara>
  <simpara>
   Although we have taken great care in ensuring that all of the information in
   the manual is correct, it is possible that some errors crept in. Please do
   inform the PHP-GTK documentation group: &email.phpgtkdoc; in case you
   encounter such errors. If something you want is not present in the manual, 
   do not hesitate to post your question to PHP-GTK-General mailing list: 
   &email.phpgtk;.
  </simpara>
  <simpara>
   This manual was produced using a modified version of the Docbook DTD. The
   modifications were made to document the object system used by PHP-GTK 2 in an
   easier manner. The XML basis for each class and their methods was initially
   generated automatically from the PHP-GTK 2 source code, and is updated via
   PHP5's Reflection to ensure that the documentation stays in-sync with the
   source.
  </simpara>
  <simpara>
   The XML generator was written by &link.andrei; (the original author of
   PHP-GTK itself) and was modified by &link.cweiske;. The documentation is
   transformed from its XML source into various other formats using
   <acronym>XSL</acronym> stylesheets as well as a host of other tools. The
   manual build system is maintained by &link.steph;.
  </simpara>
  <simpara>
   We hope you enjoy reading the manual as much as we enjoyed making it!
  </simpara>
</book>
